Guide to the Daniel G. Sisler papers, 1929- 1995
Sisler, Daniel G. papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Daniel G. Sisler papers, 1929-1995
21-1-2825
Sisler, Daniel Gene.
4.1cubic ft.
Correspondence, publications, awards, course materials, and biographical materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, subject files, clippings, photographs, honors and awards, memorabilia, academic writing, and other papers pertaining to the personal life and professional career of Daniel Sisler.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Agricultural Resources and Managerial Economics, New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences at Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, subject files, clippings, photographs, honors and awards, memorabilia, academic writing, and other papers pertaining to the personal life and professional career of Daniel Sisler.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Sisler, Daniel Gene.; Cornell University -- Faculty.; Cornell University; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences -- Faculty.; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences
Subjects:
Agriculture -- Study and teaching.; Agricultural resources -- Study and teaching.; Agricultural economics -- Study and teaching.; Agriculture -- Study and teaching; Universities and colleges -- Faculty
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Related collections: Carol Sisler papers, #4925, http://resolver.library.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/EADresolver?id=RMM04925.
CONTAINER LIST
- Personal files
  - Childhood to graduate studies
    - Dan's Baby Book, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - High School, 1947-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Includes, diplomas, certificates, clippings and yearbooks.
    - Dan - Scouts, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Includes scouting merit badges.
    - Dan's Family, 1951-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes letters between family members.1
    - USAF and Reunion, 1950-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes reunion book, correspondence and photo; also disability correspondence incl. "Line of Duty Investigation".
    - USAF Japan and Korea, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes many black and white photos, postcards, memorabilia; letter of appreciation; maps.
    - USAF Survival Training, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes black and white photos (Colorado), personal notebook, instructions, clippings.
    - USAF, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Includes correspondence with Veterans Admin about disability/blindness, and graduate agricultural studies.
    - Cornell and Purdue, 1961-1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes correspondence about finding jobs with blindness, Cornell alumni newsletters, clippings.
  - Adulthood to retirement
    - Letters from Dan's friends and students, 1985-1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dan Fishing, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Includes article in Cornell Alumni News.
    - Dan - Friends, 1950-1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Includes wedding photo, various letters and pamphlets.
    - Grandchildren, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes one card.
    - Photographs, 1929-1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Includes family photographs throughout lifetime.
    - Memorabilia (1), 1982-1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes humor, articles, Edgerton Career Teaching Award, dept. newsletters
    - Memorabilia (2), 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Includes 1993 Teaching Award, reunion booklet, dept. correspondence, newsletters.
    - Humor, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Includes collection of humorous articles and anecdotes.
    - Letters to Blind Student, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Includes correspondence to encourage blind student in Argentina.
    - Ag Econ Fellowship, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Setting up fund to finance grad assistantship.
    - Daily Sun Articles, 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Includes 1982 front page article and 1989 commemorative issue recounting 1969 student dissent.
    - Purdue Braille Notebook, Undated (Box 1)
      Looseleaf notebook in binder with Braille graphs produced by Dr. Sisler and used to learn fundamental, economic principles.
- Teaching and advising
  - Course Outlines, materials and exams
    - First Prelim Ag Ec 100, 1962-1992, 1962-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes prelims and notes for Ag Ec 50, 100, 150.
    - Final Exams 1965-1992, 1965-1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Final exams for Ag Ec 100, Ag Ec 150.
    - Ag Ec 150 - Great Plains Wheat Master, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Ag Ec 150 - The Corn Belt Master, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Ag Ec 150 - Cotton Belt Master, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Ag Ec 150 - The Northeast Master, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Ag Ec 150 - Rural NY State's Ag Districts Master, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Ag Ec 150 - Ag of the Empire Master, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Ag Ec 150 - Regions of the US Master, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Ag Ec 150 - California Grape Growers Story Master, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Ag Ec 150 - Cesar Chavez Master, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Ag Ec 150 - Grazing and Irrigated Crops Crops Master, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Ag Ec 150 - Pacific Coast Master, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Ag Ec 150 - Agriculture in the Communist Giants, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Ag Ec 100 - Full Year Sample Lectures (1), 1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Ag Ec 100 - Full Year Sample Lectures (2), 1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Ag Ec 100 Course Syllabus and Materials, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Includes Intro to Global Economic Issues syllabus; course packet; comparative advantage problem set.
    - Ag Ec 100 "Take Note" Lecture Notes, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Includes syllabus and "Take Note" lecture notes for each week of semester.
    - Introduction to Global Issues of Agricultural Economics, Undated (Box 2)
      Prof. Sisler's book of readings for Ag Ec 100
    - Sample Questions PhD Exam, 1968-1989 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Ag Ec 717 - 83:1 Course Outline, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Research Methods in Ag Economics.
    - Ag Ec 717 - 83:2 List of Important References and Topics, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Ag Ec 717 - 83:3 Exercise 1, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Ag Ec 717 - 83:4 Exercise 3, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Ag Ec 717 - 83:5 What is Science?, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Ag EC 717 - 83:6 Definitions of Experiment, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Ag Ec 717 - 83:7 Excerpts from Ferber and Verdorn, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Ag Ec 717 - 83:8 The All Too Human Enterprise Called Science., 1983 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Ag Ec 717 - Philosophy and Scientific Methods, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Ag Ec 717 -83:9 Some Important Concepts, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Ag Ec 717 - 83:10 Analyzing an Argument, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Ag Ec 717 - 83:12 Abstract from MS Thesis in Ag Econ, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Ag Ec 717 - AJAE Abstracts, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      "Award winning theses"
    - Ag Ec 717 - Basic Economic Concepts and their Measurement, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Ag Ec 717 - 83:14 Exercise 1 Examples, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Ag Ec 717 Problem Set #2, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Ag Ec 717 Sampling Concepts and Methods, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Ag Ec 717 Impacts of Investment, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Ag Ec 717 Simulation, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Ag Ec 717 Tomek AJAE Article, Waugh Article, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Advising
    - Carlos Roja, Advisee, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Includes correspondence before and during Mr Rojas time at Cornell under Prof Sisler.
    - Faculty Advising Handbook, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Ashraf, Khalid, 1964-1972 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Includes dept. correspondence about Prof Sisler's advisee, plus PhD of Mr. Ashraf. Note on folder says: "First graduate student Dr. Sisler had!"
    - Jan Low (1), 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Includes correspondence between Prof Sisler and Jan Low, dept. info regarding PhD status. Note on folder says: "Typical Sisler PhD".
    - Jan Low (2), 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Untitled Cassette Tape, 1987-11-02; TR-15916 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Acknowledgements, Undated"> (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Student acknowledgements of Dr. Sisler in theses.
    - Student Correspondence (1), 1979-1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Student Correspondence (2), 1974-1985 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Student Correspondence (3), 1972-1981 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Includes much international correspondence.
    - Student Correspondence (4), 1972-1981 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Undergraduate - general
    - Undergraduate teaching - quality, 1965-1992 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Includes review of reward system for teachers; several reports on instruction - evaluation, recognition, professionalism.
- Publications
  - Authored by Sisler
    - Publications (1), 1959-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Includes articles, book chapters, reports written by Daniel G. Sisler.
    - Publications (2), 1959-1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Publications (3), 1971-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Publications (4), 1970-1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Publications (5), 1975-1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Ag Policy, Econ Development and Nutritional Status of Children in Nepal, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Includes completed manuscript of research paper.
    - The Whole Food Situation - What is the US Role?, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Includes completed manuscript and graphs.
    - Rubber or Rice? The Dilemma of Many Developing Nations, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Includes completed article manuscript. Co-authored with David Blandford.
    - Alternative Sources of Economic Growth, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Includes manuscript for symposium paper. Co-authored with Barclay G. Jones.
    - Thesis: Direct Production Payments in the Feed-Grain-Livestock Sector of American Agriculture, 1962 (Box 4)
      Bound thesis.
  - CIIFAD (Cornell Institute for International Food and Agricultural Development)
    - Expenses 1989-90 CIIFAD, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Includes trip expenses and correspondence for CIIFAD.
    - CIIFAD Background Papers, 1989-1992 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Includes proposal to establish and fund CIIFAD, draft of mission statement, related research and correspondence about seminars.
    - CIIFAD Uganda Trip, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Includes travel preparations, correspondence, program proposals and trip report for Uganda trip.
- Awards and memorabilia
  - Physical awards
    - Friends of Cornell Hockey, Undated; MU-1869 (Box 3)
      Wooden plaque: "Dan and Carol Sisler Pacesetter".
    - Purdue University honorary doctorate, 1989-12-17; MU-1870 (Box 3)
      Fold out presentation case, one side describing Dr. Sisler's achievements, the other containing honorary Doctor of Agriculture.
    - 1993 Northeast Regional Award, 1993; MU-1871 (Box 3)
      Wooden plaque, "Award for Excellence in College and University Teaching in the Food and Agricultural Sciences."
    - Liberty Hyde Bailey Professor, 1987-07-01; MU-1872 (Box 3)
      Award mounted in glass and wood.
    - Professor of the Year Award, 1982-07-13; MU-1873 (Box 3)
      Certificate, Cornell, awarded by Council for Advancement and Support of Education.
    - Outstanding Professor Award, 1963-1964; MU-1874 (Box 3)
      Wooden plaque awarded by College of Agriculture.
    - Service to American/World Agriculture, 1989-07-31; MU-1875 (Box 3)
      Wooden plaque: "In Appreciation for Service to American/World Agriculture. National Association of County Agricultural Agents, Somerset NJ."
    - Edgerton Career Teaching Award, 1992; MU-1876 (Box 3)
      Award mounted in glass and wood, in brown box: "In recognition of a career of dedicated teaching and counseling of students" in CALS.
  - Memorabilia
    - Program for the Visit of Professors to the Republic of China, 1990-05-17-1990-05-23 (Box 3)
      "Program for the visit of Professors of Cornell University to the Republic of China for the Inauguration of the 8th President and Vice President of the Republic of China." Spiral bound pamphlet, 4 x 6".
    - Guest Book, 1989-12-15 (Box 3)
      Brown guest book housed in a Hallmark box; inscribed "Guests of Dan Sisler". No occasion noted.
    - Book: Distinguished Teachers on Effective Teaching, 1986 (Box 3)
      Editor, Peter G. Beidler.
    - Correspondence About Awards (1), 1967-1992 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Includes official awards correspondence, letters of congratulations, invitations to lecture, personal correspondence.
    - Correspondence About Awards (2), 1967-1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Purdue, 1977-1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Includes 1977 "Old MastersProgram" correspondence, schedule. Also, Honorary Doctorate Commencement booklets; official CU photo.
    - Material for Awards (1), 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Includes CV, biographical info, photo, authored reports.
    - Material for Awards (2), 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)